Guide to the Tacie Dejanikus papers, 1967-1992 MS2156
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Tacie Dejanikus papers
1967-1992
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Dejanikus, Tacie
MS2156
4.25 Linear Feet
Collection contains correspondence, research notes, articles, pamphlets, periodicals, news clippings, audio cassette tapes, banners, tee shirts, books, buttons (informational artifacts) and photographs. These materials range in date from 1967- 90 (bulk 1975 -85). It includes organizational and personal staff information about the Off Our Backs collective, a feminist journal; activities, informational, and promotional material for social and civic activism groups including Women's Liberation Zap Action Brigade,"ZAP," the American University's Women's Union, women's health, health clinics and various feminist conferences; memorabilia from the National Committee to Free Sharon Kowalski, interviews and lectures of feminist writers, and a variety of feminist and lesbian publications.
Restrictions on Access
Some records may be restricted.
Acquisition Information
In 2005, Tacie Dejanikus donated this collection to George Washington University.
Historical or Biographical Note
Tacie Dejanikus (1952 ca. -), a social and political activist, fought for women's and gay and lesbian rights as part of numerous organizations in the Washington, D.C. area. She wrote for feminist journals, participated in protest marches, and chaired social and politically minded organizations. Dejanikus lived in Chevy Chase, Maryland as a child at 7102 Ridgewood Avenue. In her late twenties, she joined the "Off Our Backs" collective, a D.C. based feminist journal. Over the next decade, her activities included interviewing various feminists and lesbians in D.C., writing for "Off Our Backs," and participating in protest activities throughout the area. Dejanikus and five other women from the Women's Liberation Zap Action Brigade were arrested on April 23, 1981, for disrupting a U.S. Senate hearing discussing the "Human Life Bill." All were released on bond for one hundred dollars and stood trial on July 6, 1981. Dejanikus continued her social and political activism, but professional disagreements compelled her to leave the "Off Our Backs" collective in 1985. In 1988 she helped form and co-chair the National Committee to Free Sharon Kowalski. She remained involved until 1991 when the Minnesota appeals court returned Sharon Kowalski to her partner Karen Thompson's custody. Throughout the course of her activities, Dejanikus protested for civil rights and health care concerns, including breast cancer, AIDS, and birth control. These papers document her and other's activities giving researchers a window into feminist and lesbian concerns as debated and protested in the Washington, D.C. area.
Collection Scope and Content
This collection contains correspondence, research notes, articles, pamphlets, periodicals, news clippings, audio cassette tapes, banners, tee shirts, books, buttons (informational artifacts) and photographs. These materials range in date from 1967- 90 (bulk 1975 -85). It includes organizational and personal staff information about the Off Our Backs collective, a feminist journal; activities, informational, and promotional material for social and civic activism groups including Women's Liberation Zap Action Brigade,"ZAP," the American University's Women's Union, women's health, health clinics and various feminist conferences; memorabilia from the National Committee to Free Sharon Kowalski, interviews and lectures of feminist writers, and a variety of feminist and lesbian publications.
Please note: each box in this collection contains material from many different series. This explains, for example, why the box listing for series 4 starts with box 1, but folder 22. The previous folders in box 1 are from different series and are listed elsewhere in the finding aid.
Collection Organization
Organized into five series: Off Our Backs, Social and Civic Activism, The National Committee to Free Sharon Kowalski, Interviews and Lectures, and Publications.
Gay rights; Sexuality & culture; Protest movements; Civil rights; Lesbian and gay experience; Lesbian feminism; Feminist theory; Audiocassettes; Photographs; Rape; Gay men -- Washington (D.C.); Washington (D.C.); Lesbians -- Washington (D.C.); Dejanikus, Tacie
- Off Our Backs, 1973-1985; Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains correspondence, statements, memoranda, notes, publications, and a tee-shirt. They range in date from 1973- 85, and represent Dejanikus' involvement in the Off Our Backs Organization. This series includes select publications of "Off Our Backs" from 1973-84. Official and personal materials from the organization are placed before "Off Our Backs" publications.
  - Detert - Moriarty, Judith, 07/27/1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Off Our Backs 1984 and 1985, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Off Our Backs Management, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Off Our Backs, A Women's News Journal, 07/1973-12/1977 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Off Our Backs, A Women's News Journal, 01/1978-06/1978 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Off Our Backs, A Women's News Journal, 07/1978-01/1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Off Our Backs, A Women's News Journal, 05/1979-11/1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Off Our Backs, A Women's News Journal, 12/1979-05/1981 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Off Our Backs, A Women's News Journal, 06/1983-12/1983 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Off Our Backs, A Women's News Journal, 01/1984-05/1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Off Our Backs [1/2], 1974-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Off Our Backs [2/2], 1974-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Off Our Backs, photograph, 1974-1983 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - [Off Our Backs] Budget 1983 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Off Our Backs [T-shirt], undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Social and Civic Activism, 1975-1990; Series 2; 2 Linear feet
  This series contains news clippings, pamphlets, memoranda, notes, correspondence, and buttons (informational artifacts). They range in date from 1975-90 and represent a wide range of women's, lesbian and gay rights issues including the activist organization ZAP, health care concerns, American University's Women's Union, and protests against pornographic films.
  - American University Women's Union [1/2], 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American University Women's Union [2/2], 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Donna Jean Walters, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Feminist and Lesbian Literature and Activities, 1979-1987 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Movie Protest "Charlotte", 1975 ca. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Pornography and Movie Protest, 1981 ca. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Social Activism, 1979 ca. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Publication workshop, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Women's health and health clinics, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Culturally Yours, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - D.C. Feminism, Correspondence, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - D.C. Feminism 70s and 80s, 1980-1990 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Feminist resource, Notebook Project, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Outreach list of duplicates, 1987 ca. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Women make great leaders [bumper sticker], undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - ZAP [women's liberation zap action brigade] 1981 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    General note
    Contains court summons for Dejanikus and other related items to her arrest.
  - Social and Civic Activism, undated (Box 6)
    Collection of buttons (informational artifacts)
  - Trays of buttons (informational artifacts), undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Contains 4 trays of buttons (informational artifacts). Topics include protesting for gay rights, breast cancer awareness, AIDS awareness, presidential candidates, and domestic violence. Includes one button from the National Committee to Free Sharon Kowalski.
- The National Committee to Free Sharon Kowalski, 1988-1991; Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet
  This series consists of an signed book, certificate, banners, tee shirts and buttons (informational artifacts) from the National Committee to Free Sharon Kowalski co-chaired by Tacie Dejanikus from 1988-91. In 1983 Sharon Kowalski was permanently disabled in a car accident and a legal battle ensued over guardianship between Donald and Della Kowalski, Sharon's parents, and Karen Thompson, Sharon's partner. Supporters of Karen Thompson formed The National Committee to Free Sharon to support Thompson's efforts in removing Sharon from her parent's custody and placing her under Thompson's own care. The court would place Sharon Kowalski under Thompson's care in December of 1991.
  - "Why can't Sharon Kowalksi Come Home" By Karen Thompson and Julie Andrzejewski [autographed], 1988 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - National Committee to Free Sharon Kowalski, 1989-1992 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Includes a pamphlet, certificate, and correspondence
  - Bring Sharon Home [T-shirt], undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Let there be love, Free Sharon Kowalski [T-shirt], undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Nat Comm to Free Sharon Kowalski [banner], undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Free Sharon Kowalski [banner], undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Free Sharon Kowalski [banner], undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Image [may be of Karen Thompson], undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Interviews and Lectures, 1975 ca.-1985 ca.; Series 4; 0.75 Linear feet
  This series contains notes, newspaper clippings, photographs, and audio cassette tapes. This includes news clippings, notes, and interviews with Michelle Cliff regarding her book, "Claiming An Identity They Taught Me To Despise." Also included are interview notes with Stephanie Liu concerning her thoughts on being a lesbian and personal correspondence, photographs, and news clippings sent by Liu to Dejanikus after Liu moved to Hong Kong.
  - Lesbian Oral History, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Michelle Cliff, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Michelle Cliff, photograph, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Stephanie Liu's Interview, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Stephanie Liu's Interview, Newspaper, 09/28/1979 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Stephanie Liu's Interview, photographs, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - [Taber], Martha, 03/10/1983 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Laurie McLaughlin's speech, anti-rape week, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Interviews and Lectures, undated (Box 4)
  - Lesbian Rights Project, Roberta Achtenberg, 11/22, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Roberta Achtenberg, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Rita Arauz, Latina Lesbians, 11/20/1982 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Arlene - DREDF [KiCorbett?], undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Asian lesbians, 11/22/1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - JEB [Joan E. Biren], 06/29/1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Michelle Cliff, 02/21/1981 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - K. Corbett, Disability Rights Edu + Defense [Fund?], 01/23/1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - DES [Action ?] National Nancy Address, 11/22/1982 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Feminist Law Collective, 08/17/1982 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Feminist Law Collective, 08/17/1982 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Feminist Law Collective, 08/17/1982 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Marcia Freedman, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Debra [George], undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Debra [George], 10/20/1981 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Household Workers Project, undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - ICI -3, Natalie + Carol, 11/22/1982 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - ICI -3, 11/22/1982 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - ICI - A women's place (4), 11/18/1982 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - ICI - 4, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Ivan Illich vs The Women, Berkeley, U[niversity] of CA [California], 11/19/1982 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Ivan Illich vs The Women, 11/19/1982 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Interview with Rita Jolie [Mulier?], Belgium women from Lilith, 04/20/1982 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Linda Krieger, 11/15/1982 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - cont'd Linda Krieger, 11/15/1982 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Laura X, Women Against Jamie Baldino Aga[?]t, 11/11/1982 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Laura X, 11/11/1982 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - A reading, Lesbian Studies, undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Ellen [Mutari?], Where's movement going., 10/11/1982 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Janet Walkup, WAVPM, 11/15/1982 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Natural Women's mailing list, 11/23/1982 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - N. Polikoff - child custody, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - N. Polikoff - child custody, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Diana Russel, Rape in marriage, 11/11/1982 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Diana Russel, 11/11/1982 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Carol Seajay, 11/16/1982 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Carol Seajay, 11/16/1982 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - "Sally" - sexual harassment [1/2], undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
    This cassette tape was attached to another cassette tape.
  - "Sally" - on sexual harassment at her college [2/2], undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Stephanie [1/2], undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Stephanie [2/2], undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Interview with Marlene Wicks, one of the oob [Off Our Backs] founders [1/2], 01/07/1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Interview with Marlene, co-founder of oob [Off Our Backs] [2/2], 01/07/1980 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Alice Wolfsin, CDRR, 11/17/1982 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Alice Wolfsin, cont'd, 11/23/1982 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Alice Wolfsin, 11/23/1982 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Untitled cassette tapes, undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
    4 unmarked cassette tapes
- Publications, 1967-1990; Series 5; 0.5 Linear feet
  The materials in this series includes periodicals, guides, a coloring book, a music songbook, informational booklets from 1967-90. The majority of these publications are from feminist, lesbian, or women's groups
  - "Abortion, a women's right to choose" A guide to abortion in the D.C. area, Washington's Women's Center, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Amazon Quarterly, "Lesbian Lifestyles" vol. 1, no. 4; vol. 2, no. 1, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - The Black Scholar "Black Women's Liberation" vol. 4, no. 6-7, 03/1973-04/1973 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - "Clara and Concha in a nursing home romance" by j.d., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - "Cunt Coloring Book" Tee Corinne, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Gap Tooth Girlfriends: An Anthology, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Gold Flower, vol. 3, no. 11, 03/1974 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Heliotrope, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Heresies, a feminist publication on art and politics, vol. 2, no. 4, issue 8 "Third World Women, the politics of being other", 1979 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Heresies, vol. 3, no. 1, issue 9 "Organized, women, divided", 1980 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    a feminist publication on art and politics
  - "I am my Lover" by Joani Blank and Honey Lee Cottrell, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Lavender Women, lesbian/feminist newspaper, vol. 4, no. 5, 12/1975 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - The Lesbin Tide, 01/1976-04/1976 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    A feminist lesbian publication, written by and for the rising tide of women today
  - "Love, politics, and rescue in lesbian relationship" an essay by Diana Rabenold, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Love your enemy? the debate between heterosexual feminism and political lesbianism, 04/1981 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - "Loving Women" by the Nomadic Sisters, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Marilyn Gayle, "dyke music," a songbook, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - "More than a choice, women talk about abortion", 1978 ca. (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Motive, vol. 32 no. 1, "Lesbian/Feminist issue", 1972 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Notes from the third year: women's liberation, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - "the playbook for women about sex" by Joani Blank, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Redstockings, "Feminist Revolution", 1975 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - "Salir a la luz como lesbiana de color" or Coming out colored by Maya Chumu, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Scum Manifesto, Valerie Solanas edition, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Strong women's conference, follow up booklet, 11/1977 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    Graphics support from Off Our Backs
  - Women's liberation: an anthropological view, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - "Women locked up" Women, a journal of liberation, vol. 3, no. 3, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - "Women organizing the office" by the Women's Work Project, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Moonstorm, Lesbian Feminist Newsletter for Women, issue 23, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - The Wree-View, bulletin of women for racial and economic equality, 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    2 issues: May [pilot issue], 1976 and Septemeber/October 1978, vol. 3, no. 4